Finding Aid for National Organization for Women, Michigan Conference Records, 1969-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Margot Duley-Morrow, 1973-1984
  - Michigan Now Coalitions
    - Women's Assembly III
      - Agendas, Minutes, Treasurers Reports, July 1982-April, 1983 (scattered) (Box 4)
      - Legislation and Education, Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - Memos and Mailings, Miscellaneous, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
      - Future Directions (undated) (Box 4)
      - Lists of Participants (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Michigan Women's Hall of Fame
      - General Information (Box 4)
      - Nominating Procedure (Box 4)
    - Solidarity Day Rally, September, 1981 (Box 4)
    - National Regional, and Out of State NOW
      - Lists of National and 50 State Leaders (Box 4)
      - National Conference, Detroit, 1977 (Box 4)
      - Regional Conferences
        - Southbend, Indiana (informal), September 1979 (Box 4)
        - Ann Arbor (planning committee), April 1980 (Box 4)
        - Cincinnati, April 1983 (Box 4)
      - Regional, Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - Out-of-State, Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Clippings, 1967; 1979-1983
    Regarding the Clippings series it should be noted that there are disappointingly few articles about Michigan NOW, though many on women's issues in Michigan and general Michigan politics. Many of the clippings concern the impact of the Reagan Administration's social policy on women. Most of the clippings are dated.
    - File, 1980 (Box 4)
    - ERA
      - From File, 1980 (Box 4)
      - From Lansing State Journal (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Michigan NOW and Michigan Women's Issues (Box 5)
    - Michigan Politics (Box 5)
    - Out-of-State and National NOW (Box 5)
    - Women's Issues, miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Gay Rights (Box 5)
    - New Right/Moral Majority (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Ephemera, circa 1970-1983
    The Ephemera series is composed of brochures, flyers, and miscellaneous mailings from Michigan organizations (or state branches of national organizations). This material illustrates both Michigan NOW's network of affiliations and concerns, and the activities of these diverse social justice, civil rights, and women's groups.
    - ACLU, Michigan (Box 5)
    - People for the American Way (Box 5)
    - Catholics for Free Choice (Box 5)
    - Center of Peace and Conflict Studies, Wayne State (Box 5)
    - Coalition of Labor union Women (CLUW) (Box 5)
    - Comparable Worth Task Force (CWTF) Lansing (Box 5)
    - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC)/Democratic Socialists of America (DSA) (Box 5)
    - Michigan Civil Rights Commission (Box 5)
    - Michigan Coalition for Human Rights (Box 5)
    - Michigan Network of Runaway Youth Services (Box 5)
    - Michigan Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights (Box 5)
    - Michigan Reproductive Freedom Council (Box 5)
    - Michigan Republican Women's Task Force (Box 5)
    - Michigan Welfare Reform Coalition (Box 5)
    - Michigan Women's Campaign Fund (Box 5)
    - Michigan Women's Commission (Box 5)
    - Michigan Women's Political Caucus (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Michigan Women's Organizations (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Michigan Organizations (Box 5)
    - National Black Child Development Institute, Detroit Metro Affiliate (Box 5)
    - National Health Service, Michigan Coalition for (Box 5)
    - National Women's Conference (Box 5)
    - National Women's Education fund (Box 5)
    - Planned parenthood of Michigan (Box 5)
    - Safehouse, Ann Arbor, Michigan (Box 5)
    - Violence Against Women Committee, Ann Arbor, Michigan (Box 5)
    - Voice of Reason, Franklin, Michigan (Box 5)
    - Women in Action, Ann Arbor, Michigan (Box 5)
    - Women's Equity Action League (WEAL), Michigan (Box 5)
    - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, Michigan (Box 5)
    - Women's Justice Center, Detroit (Box 5)
  - Nan Frost-Welmers (President) files, 1977-1979
    The Chapter Information folder in the Nan Frost-Welmers series is a notebook containing forms for each local chapter which give information on the regularity of meetings, lists of officers, and other miscellaneous points. (Additional, and more substantive, information about local chapters will be found elsewhere in this collection). The State Newsletter folder includes meeting announcements, lists of officers, a report on "pro-choice" activities, a report on Michigan NOW's police, feminist song-lyrics, a 1977-1978 list of accomplishments, and miscellaneous material. Many of the documents in the Coalition series are flyers and mass-mailings, but the subseries also includes meeting agendas and not a little correspondence.
    - Local Chapter Information (Box 5)
    - State Newsletter: Misc. Correspondence, Suggestions for Articles (Box 5)
    - Coalitions
      - Bakke Decision, Michigan Coalition to Overturn the (Box 5)
      - Coalition for Non-Sexist Education (Box 5)
      - Coalition of Labor Union Women: Oakland Press Boycott, J.P. Stevens Textile Products, 1978 (Box 5)
      - Coalitions, Miscellaneous (Box 5)
      - ERAmerica, Michigan (Box 5)
      - Michigan Coalition Against Domestic Violence (Box 5)
      - Michigan Human Rights Coalition (Box 5)
      - Women Organized to Meet Existing Needs (WOMEN) (Box 5)
  - Rhonda Drinan (Chapter Developer) files, 1977-1979
    The Rhonda Drinan files illustrate the state conference's role in energizing, disciplining, educating, and coordinating the local chapters of NOW, as well as the triumphs and traumas of the local chapters themselves. This series provides a fascinating glimpse into the institutional mechanics of the National Organization for Women.
    The Correspondence folder includes communications with the national chapter coordinator and requests from women seeking to join or organize a local chapter. Correspondence with the local chapters themselves --dealing with everything from confirming Drinan's appearance at a meeting to what to do about personality conflicts within a chapter--is contained in the Chapters subseries. The Notes and Materials subseries provides an overview of the duties, goals, and accomplishments of the Chapter Developer, as well as of the problems and priorities of leading a local chapter. It includes notes on the status and state of each chapter, and agendas and notes for Drinan's meetings with chapters. Specific material worth mentioning includes "Guidelines for Starting a NOW Chapter, "The Reaction of Women to the Inferior Status of Women," the notes on "feminist burn-out, and "How to Do an Auction."
    The cornerstone of the series is the Chapters subseries. Correspondence with chapter officers and material (flyers, agendas, handouts, handbooks) sent from the chapters to document their activities form the bulk of these files, though a good deal of routine bureaucratic communication is also present. The correspondence offers occasional glimpses into the personal conflicts and friendships which had so much to do with the success or failure of local chapters. Insights are afforded, too, into the sometimes tangled bureaucracy of NOW.
    - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Notes and Materials (Box 5)
    - General (Box 5)
    - Facts of Chapter Developing
      - Management/Leadership (Box 5)
      - Consciousness Raising (including songs) (Box 5)
      - Direct Action Organizing/Priorities Setting (Box 5)
      - Fundraising (Box 5)
    - Chapter Development Retreats and Conferences
      - Lansing, February 1977 (Box 6)
      - Big Rapids, November 1977
        - General (Box 6)
        - Evaluations (Box 6)
      - MSU (including evaluations), March 1980 (Box 6)
    - Chapters
      - General Information
        - Activities Reports, 1976 (Box 6)
        - Questionnaires, 1977 (Box 6)
      - Adrian/Lenawee County (Box 6)
      - Ann Arbor/Washtenaw County (Box 6)
      - Battle Creek (Box 6)
      - Bay City (Box 6)
      - Berrien county (Box 6)
      - Big Rapids (Box 6)
      - Branch County (Box 6)
      - Copper County (Box 6)
      - Detroit (Box 6)
      - Downriver (Box 6)
      - Eastern U.P. (Box 6)
      - Flint (Box 6)
      - Grand Rapids (Box 6)
      - Howell (Box 6)
      - Jackson (Box 6)
      - Kalamazoo (Box 6)
      - Lansing (Box 6)
      - Macomb County (Box 6)
      - Marquette (Box 6)
      - Midland (Box 6)
      - Monroe County (Box 6)
      - Mt. Pleasant (Box 6)
      - Muskegon-Ottawa (Box 6)
      - Northern Oakland County (Box 6)
      - Northwest Wayne County (Box 6)
      - Oakland County (Box 6)
      - Petoskey (Box 6)
      - Port Huron (Box 6)
      - Saginaw (Box 6)
      - Traverse City (Box 6)
      - University of Michigan, Dearborn (Box 6)
  - ERA Task Force Chair (Judy Skog 1978-1979 Karen Rice, 1977-1978)
    Included in the ERA Task Force Chair files are notes from a few ERAmerica meetings during 1979 and the group of "Alerts" from 1977 (in the Announcements, etc. folder).
    - Correspondence, January, 1978-May, 1979 (Box 6)
    - ERAmerica Meeting Notes, 1979 (Box 6)
    - Announcements, Mailings, Local Activists, 1977-1979 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Shirley Monson (President) files, 1976-1977
    The Shirley Monson series includes scattered correspondence, minutes, and subject files.
    - Correspondence (scattered) (Box 6)
    - SCC Minutes and Budgetary Information (scattered), September, 1977
      - ERA (Box 6)
      - EOC and Affirmation Action (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Michigan Now Local Chapter Files, 1969-1979
    The Michigan NOW Local Chapter Files (1969-1979) apparently have had an odd past. The documents dated 1969-1977 indicate that for these years the files were those of the Midwest Regional office of NOW. From late 1977 through 1979, the files seem to have been used by the Michigan NOW state president (Nan Frost-Welmers). Why the files were transferred is unclear, though it may have been part of the general reorganization when the Great Lakes Regional office was created or it may reflect a shift of the bureaucratic responsibility for convening local chapters. In any case, the files are a strange amalgam, especially since not every chapter folder contains documents from both periods. The quantity of material relating to the several chapters varies tremendously between them as well.
    However, the files are a gold mine, containing rich (if scattered) veins of fascinating records. Even the bureaucratic forms are interesting, in that they (along with some of the correspondence) provide an account of the lengthy and somewhat convoluted procedures for chartering a chapter, reporting elections, and the like, as well as of the efforts expended to generate interest in forming chapters. Other material includes announcements of chapter activities, chapter meeting agendas and minutes, questionnaires and surveys, chapter histories and bylaws, and more. Correspondence illustrating the Regional office's role in the NOW hierarchy is also present, as are communications between Frost-Welmers and local chapter leaders.
    - Adrian (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor/Washtenaw County (Box 6)
    - Battle Creek (Box 6)
    - Bay City (Box 6)
    - Berrien County (Box 6)
    - Branch County (Box 6)
    - Big Rapids (Box 6)
    - Coldwater (Box 6)
    - Copper County (Box 6)
    - Detroit (Box 6)
    - Downriver (Box 6)
    - Flint (Box 6)
    - Grand Rapids (Box 6)
    - Holland (Box 6)
    - Jackson (Box 6)
    - Kalamazoo (Box 6)
    - Lansing (Box 6)
    - Lenawee county (Box 6)
    - Livingston County (Box 6)
    - Macomb county (Box 6)
    - Marquette (Box 6)
    - Michigan Chapter (Box 6)
    - Midland (Box 6)
    - Midwestern Wayne County (Box 6)
    - Mt. Pleasant (Box 6)
    - Muskegon (Box 6)
    - Northwest Wayne County (Schoolcraft) (Box 6)
    - Oakland County (Box 6)
    - Port Huron (Box 6)
    - Saginaw (Box 6)
    - Sault Ste. Marie (Box 6)
    - Traverse City (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Doris Little, Macomb County NOW, 1975-1982
    Doris Little capped her long involvement with Macomb County NOW by serving as president of the chapter for the 1981-1982 terms. A retired professional whose other commitments included MENSA and Toastmasters, Little was known throughout Michigan NOW for her feminist activities, and helped to represent the Michigan Conference at the United Nations Women's Conference in Copenhagen (1980). The records in this subgroup mainly reflect the period during Little's presidency of the Macomb chapter. The division into Personal and Macomb County NOW series is somewhat artificial, as her personal life was quite intertwined with her identity as a NOW activist. Little died of cancer in December 1982.
    - Personal
      The Correspondence, Scrapbook, Speeches, and Engagement Books folders are the most substantive, and together comprise a portrait of a terrifically energetic, dedicated, and articulate woman. Her engagement books and calendars bear witness to the extraordinary range and number of her commitments. The Speeches folder includes a transcript of Little's testimony before a congressional budget impact hearing and a tape of an interview of her on a local radio program. The scrapbook includes clippings, correspondence, conference and meeting programs, flyers, and awards; it is something of a capsule history of the first half of her tenure as chapter president.
      - Biographical (Box 7)
      - Correspondence (Box 7)
      - Scrapbook (includes correspondence), 1981; 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Speeches, Interviews, etc., 1975-1982 (Box 7)
      - Engagement Books, Calendars, etc. (Box 7)
      - Meetings Attended, 1982 (Box 7)
      - Awards (Box 7)
      - Toastmasters (Box 7)
      - Clippings
        - Women (Box 7)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Macomb County NOW, 1981-1982
      Macomb County NOW subseries. The folder of board meeting minutes and the notebook, along with the scrapbook folders from the Personal series, solidly document the priorities, actions, and problems during one year of a local chapter's existence. The ad hoc committee material presents a more detailed look into one such priority and problem. With the corresponding newsletters (found elsewhere in this collection), Macomb County NOW becomes the best documented chapter in this collection.
      - Minutes of Board Meetings and Treasurer's Reports, May 1981-April 1982 (Box 7)
      - Notebook (Box 7)
      - Ad Hoc Committee re Producing Cable TV Show, February 4, 1982 (Box 7)
      - State Convention Material, June 1982 (Box 7)
      - Women's Assembly III Notebook (Box 7)
      - Parliamentary Procedure Workshop, undated (Box 7)
      - Tapes of Guest Speakers, November, 1981; July 1982 (Box 7)
      - Detroit News Sex Discrimination Controversy, circa 1979-1980 (Box 7)
      - ERA
        - From "Countdown" Folder (Box 7)
        - Walkathon, Financial Accounts, 1980 (Box 7)
        - Walkathon, Pledge Collection, 1982 (Box 7)
      - Public Relations Notebook (Box 7)
      - Ephemera
        - Macomb County Organizations (Box 7)
        - Miscellaneous Women's Organizations and Events (Box 7)
        - Local Politicians (Box 7)
        - Miscellaneous Feminist (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Photographs (Box 7)
      These photographs, removed from Little's scrapbook, contain informal pictures of three major feminist events, and informal portraits of Little and Carol King (at the time, King was the Michigan Conference's representative on the National NOW board of directors; she had already served as president of Michigan NOW and president of Macomb County NOW). Included are photographs of United Nations Women's Conference, Copenhagen 1980 ERA Rally, Detroit, 1981 National NOW Conference, 1981
  - Virginia Harris, Oakland County NOW, 1973-1980
    Virginia Harris served in various posts in the Oakland County chapter, including treasurer (1973-1975) and board member (1975-1976, 1977-1979). The material is largely scattered, with the most significant component being that of the Board of Directors Meeting Minutes.
    - Officers, Planning Calendars, Bylaws, 1973-1976 (Box 8)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes October, 1973-July, 1977 January, 1978-April, 1980 (Box 8)
    - Treasurer's Reports and Budgets, April, 1976-December, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Metro Detroit Leadership Training conference, September, 1975 (Box 8)
    - Dr. Don R. Krohn Sexual Assault controversy, circa July, 1977 (Box 8)
    - Original Chapter Mailing List, 1973 (Box 8)
    - National NOW Conference, Detroit, 1977 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - NOW Newsletters, 1971-1984 (scattered)
    Detailed information about the month to month operations of Michigan NOW is available in the chapter newsletters, which announce Conference policy and statewide actions to the membership as well as communicate issues and events of local concern. Moreover, the local chapter newsletters in this collection cover a longer chronological period than do the newsletters of the state organization (although coverage varies from chapter to chapter). All in all, the local chapter newsletters might be the best place to start a study of Michigan NOW, since they provide easily accessible coverage of the accomplishments, personality, personnel, and evolution of the Conference.
    - Battle Creek, 1972-1984 (Box 8)
    - Big Rapids, 1977 (Box 8)
    - Copper County, 1974-1975 (Box 8)
    - Detroit and Detroit Metro, 1971-1984; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Downriver, 1977-1984 (Box 8)
    - Eastern U.P., 1975 (Box 8)
    - Flint, 1973-1975; 1984 (Box 8)
    - Grand Rapids, 1975-1981 (Box 8)
    - Hol, 1975-1978 (Box 8)
    - Jackson, 1977-1979; 1982-1983 (Box 8)
    - Kalamazoo, 1973-1979 (Box 8)
    - Lansing, 1973-1982 (Box 8)
    - Livingston count, 1979-1982 (Box 8)
    - Macomb County, 1972-1983 (Box 8)
    - Mid, 1973-1984 (Box 8)
    - Mt. Pleasant, 1977-1979 (Box 9)
    - Muskegon-Ottawa, 1974-1979 (Box 9)
    - North Oakland County, 1982-1983 (Box 9)
    - Northwest Wayne County, 1973-1977 (Box 9)
    - Oakland County, 1976-1984 (Box 9)
    - Traverse City, 1979-1983 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, including Three Rivers; Women's Liberation Coalition; Lenawee County; Pontiac, U of M Dearborn, 1972-1984 (Box 9)
- Alicia Perez-Banuet (1997 Accession), 1972-1984
  The accession of NOW records received in 1997 from Alicia Perez-Banuet have been divided into the following series: Administrative, Legislation, Task Forces / Coalitions, and Chapters.
  This accession fills in some of the previously described gaps in the collection. Of particular interest are the files of the legislative coordinator and the files generated by various task forces and coalitions.
  - Administrative
    - Agendas and Minutes, 1972-1984; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Conference: Bay City: Social and Economic Status of Women, 1975 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, Midwest Region, 1973-1978; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, Title IX, 1979 (Box 9)
    - Development, 1972-1975 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1978-1984; undated (Box 9)
    - Scripts, including "Boy Meets Girl" (Box 9)
    - Speech (Jo Jacobs, 1983) (Box 9)
  - Legislation
    - Contacts, 1974 (Box 9)
    - State, 1975-1977 (Box 9)
    - Legislative Coordinator, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Legislative Meetings (Box 9)
    - Positions (Box 10)
    - State Health Monitor, 1974-1977 (Box 10)
    - Voting Records (Box 10)
  - Task Forces / Coalitions
    - Action Against School Board, 1974 (Box 10)
    - Affirmative Action, 1975-1976 (Box 10)
    - Contract Compliance, 1972-1973 (Box 10)
    - Education, 1974-1980; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Media Task Force, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Task Force on Sexual Harassment, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Park Time Work (Box 10)
    - Interfaith Council for Racial Justice, 1976-1977 (Box 10)
    - Kids in Need Deserve Equal Rights (KINDER), 1982-1983 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Abortion Rights Action League, 1981-1985 (Box 10)
    - Sears Action, 1975 (Box 10)
    - State Task Force on Rape, 1974 (Box 10)
    - Tri-County Coalition Against Domestic Violence, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Women and Alcohol, 1974 (Box 10)
    - W.O.M.A.N. Center, 1975-1976 (Box 10)
  - Chapters, circa 1979-1984
    - Development Conference, 1977 (Box 10)
    - Allegan County (Box 10)
    - Ann Arbor (Box 10)
    - Battle Creek (Box 10)
    - Benton Harbor / St. Joseph (Box 10)
    - Berrien County (Box 10)
    - Big Rapids (Box 10)
    - Branch County (Box 10)
    - Coldwater (Box 10)
    - Copper County (Box 10)
    - Detroit and Downriver (Box 10)
    - Eastern Upper Peninsula (Box 10)
    - Flint (Box 10)
    - Grand Rapids (Box 10)
    - Holland (Box 10)
    - Kalamazoo (Box 10)
    - Jackson (Box 10)
    - Lansing (Box 10)
    - Lenawee County (Box 10)
    - Livingston County (Box 10)
    - Marquette (Box 10)
    - Midland (Box 10)
    - Macomb (Box 10)
    - Muskegon (Box 10)
    - Northwest Wayne County (Box 10)
    - Oakland County (Box 10)
    - Petoskey (Box 10)
    - Three River (Box 10)
    - Traverse City (Box 10)
    - Wayne High School (Box 10)
- Alicia Perez-Banuet, 1972-1996
  Alicia Perez-Banuet donated her presidential files and other organizational in two accessions, 2001 (boxes 11-14) and 2004 (boxes 15-19). The 2001 accession of approximately 4 linear feet donated by the 1997-1998 president of Michigan NOW do not necessarily represent the activity of Michigan NOW during Perez-Banuet's Presidency, but rather are a collection of general organizational files as well as files from various state officers collected throughout a two decade period leading up to Perez-Banuet's time in office. Subseries derived from this material include a Topical File, Correspondence, Chapter Newsletters, Macomb County NOW records, Administrative Files, and Officer Files. The most substantial portion of the files include extensive information on the battle to maintain state funding for abortions in Michigan and the activity of the NOW Political Action Committee (PAC) through each state and national campaign and election from 1982 to 1992. Scattered throughout the Officer and Administrative series are meeting minutes, leadership lists, agendas and other materials that give insight into the operating procedures of the Michigan NOW conference for a period spanning nearly 20 years.
  The 2004 accession of five linear feet, donated by Alicia Perez-Banuet, president for Michigan NOW, 1997-1998, broadly covers the period of 1976-1996. Some older records from the 1970s and early 1980s were a part of the accession. Overlaps with previous accessions were resolved by blending materials where appropriate. The records of this accession have been arranged in subseries that reflect functioning of the organization for the ease of the researcher. Because of the decentralized nature of Michigan NOW, there are gaps in the records. However, the permanent structures, such as the State Coordinating Council and its Executive Committee, serve as focal points for activities and tie the many chapters together. The bulk of the records are from the late 1980s and early 1990s.
  - Topical File